It's only a state of mind.
Brazil is a comedy, science fiction film directed by Terry Gilliam.
Low-level bureaucrat Sam Lowry escapes the monotony of his day-to-day life through a
recurring daydream of himself as a virtuous hero saving a beautiful damsel.
Investigating a case that led to the wrongful arrest and eventual death of an innocent man instead of wanted terrorist Harry Tuttle, he meets the
woman from his daydream, and in trying to help her gets caught in a web of mistaken identities, mindless bureaucracy and lies.
Sam Lowry, played by Jonathan Pryce.
Harry Tuttle, played by Robert De Niro.
Mrs. Ida Lowry, played by Katherine Helmond.
Mr. Kurtzmann, played by Ian Holm.
Spoor, played by Bob Hoskins.
Jack Lint, played by Michael Palin.
Brazil is a 1985 dystopian science fiction black comedy film directed by Terry
Gilliam and written by Gilliam, Charles McKeown, and Tom Stoppard.
A co-production between the United Kingdom and the United States, the film stars Jonathan Pryce, Robert De Niro,
Katherine Helmond, Ian Holm, Bob Hoskins, Michael Palin, Ian Richardson, Peter Vaughan, and Kim Greist.
The film centres on Sam Lowry, a low-ranking bureaucrat trying to find a woman who appears in his dreams while he is working in a mind-numbing job and living in a small flat, set in a dystopian world in
which there is an over-reliance on poorly maintained (and rather whimsical) machines and where people found guilty of crimes are liable for the costs of their interrogation by torture.
Brazil's satire of technocracy, bureaucracy, hyper-surveillance, corporate statism, and state capitalism is reminiscent of
George Orwell's 1949 novel Nineteen Eighty-Four, and it has been called "Kafkaesque" as well as absurdist.
Sarah Street's British National Cinema (1997) described the film as a "fantasy/satire on bureaucratic
society", and John Scalzi's Rough Guide to Sci-Fi Movies (2005) described it as a "dystopian satire".
Jack Mathews, a film critic and the author of The Battle of Brazil (1987), described the film as "satirizing the
bureaucratic, largely dysfunctional industrial world that had been driving Gilliam crazy all his life".
Despite its title, the film is not about the country Brazil nor does it take place there; it is named after the recurrent theme
song, Ary Barroso's "Aquarela do Brasil", known simply as "Brazil" to British audiences, as performed by Geoff Muldaur.
Although a success in Europe, the film was unsuccessful
in its initial North American release.
It has since become a cult film.
In 1999, the British Film Institute voted Brazil the
54th greatest British film of all time.
In 2017, a poll of 150 actors, directors, writers, producers and critics for
Time Out magazine saw it ranked the 24th best British film ever.
The film explores themes of dreams, government,
bureaucracy, police state, great britain.
The tone is lighthearted and dark and thought_provoking.